KRISTINA ULICNA

PhD Candidate (final year) @ UCL

- London, United Kingdom
- kristina.smith.ulicna@gmail.com
- linkedin.com/in/KristinaUlicna
- twitter.com/KristinaUlicna
- github.com/KristinaUlicna

Computational Skills

Strongest programming language: Python Experience with deep learning strategies for <u>image analysis</u> & computer vision apps

- Fully supervised: U-Net, ConvNet, TCN
- Weakly supervised: multiple-instance
- Self supervised: generative (VQ-) VAE
- Unsupervised: k-means clustering
- Dimensionality reduction: PCA, UMAP

Skilled in "image2seq" representations & time-sequence trajectory data analysis

- Machine learning libraries: skimage, sklearn, torch, pytorch lightning, tensorflow 2.0, keras, innereye-deeplearning, btrack, HPACellSegmentator, CSBDeep
- Standard & scientific libraries: numpy, scipy, pandas, matplotlib, seaborn, pyplot, h5py, tgdm, napari, dtaidistance

Work comfortably in conda venvs, GitHub (git), iPython (jupyter) notebooks, LaTeX (overleaf) & Sigmaplot Statistics software

Analysis of **DNA sequencing** data:

- SnapGene software: vector construction
- CLC workbench: Sanger sequencing
- Nanopore sequencing platform interface

Laboratory Skills

Molecular biology & vector construction:

- PCR (RT-, colony-, sequential-, nested-)
- Plasmid preparation (mini- & midi-prep)
- Restriction endonuclease gene cloning
- · Gateway cloning & Gibson Assembly
- Preparation & purification of mRNA
- Cell-free protein synthesis (PURExpress)

Cell engineering & tissue culture:

- Stable cell transfection via lipofection or lentiviral & retroviral transduction
- Colony selection with antibiotic titration
- Tet(Dox)-inducible gene expression
- Cell fractionation & organelle isolation
- Induction of cell differentiation (DMSO)
- Cell culture (passaging) with cell lines: MDCK, HeLa, HL60, CHO, HEK-293, MCF-7/ 10A, MDA-MB-231, HMLER, LNCaP, HaCaT

Cell-based assays & imaging platforms:

 IncuCyte ZOOM live-cell analysis system cell proliferation assay with colorimetric cell viability, ratiometric [Ca2+] release & fluorimetric protein release assays

Gene expression detection methods:

- SDS-PAGE, Western (dot) blotting
- Immunocytochemistry (IF cell staining)
- Extra- & intracellular flow cytometry
- FACS-sorted clonal cell line expansion

Summary

As a PhD researcher at UCL, I apply my programming & laboratory skills in a multi-disciplinary project combining cell biology, computational single-cell tracking & interpretable deep learning. I focus on Python research development for large image data analysis to identify biological patterns influencing diverse cell cycling control mechanisms. I am a practical, detail-oriented wet-lab scientist with cell engineering background, experienced in dry-lab machine learning research applied to single-cell biology. I have demonstrated my leadership skills in individual & collective settings, which I gained through UK & US work experience in academic biomedical research groups & international bio-/medical & microscopy imaging research teams in leading technological companies, and through my involvement in volunteering & community projects.

Education

Oct 2018 -Nov 2022 (expected)

PhD in Biosciences, BBSRC LIDo DTP Programme, UCL | London, UK

- Fully-funded Doctoral Thesis: "Learning Meaningful Representations of Computationally Tracked Single-Cell Trajectories in Heterogeneous Cell Lines using Deep Generative Modelling", advised by Alan Lowe & Guillaume Charras (UCL & Turing)
- 3x merit-based scholarships: Yale School of Medicine exchange visitor (postponed)

Sep 2014 -Jul 2018

BSc Biomedical Science (Hons), King's College London | London, UK

- First Class Hons (76%) Biomedical Science with Molecular Biology Extramural Year
- Awards & Scholarships: Desmond Tutu Scholarship '14, Best Lay Article Award '15

Research Experience

Mar 2019 -Present

PhD Researcher, the "DeepTree" project @ UCL | London, UK

- · Co-developed a robust, supervision-free, deep learning-based tracking pipeline for deep lineage analysis of large time-lapse live-cell microscopy data of 2D cell lines
- Published two computational framework articles (U-Net, CNN, bTrack multi-object tracking algorithm) applicable for deep single-cell trajectory lineage reconstruction
- · Analysed multigenerational lineage trees (>20k single-cell tracks) to interpret <u>proliferation determinants</u> which predispose cells to commit to fast divider fates
- Generated explainable image-based representations of single-cell time sequences
- Directly supervised Masters project to develop an Al-based cell segmentation tool

Apr 2021 -Sep 2021

Research Intern @ Microsoft Research Cambridge | Cambridge, UK

- · Developed an Al-based end-to-end pipeline to classify subcellular protein localisation in single cells from Human Protein Atlas' dataset of weakly labelled confocal microscopy images using Azure computing & InnerEye Deep Learning OS toolkit
- Trained a competitively-performing model (MIL / SimCLR & BYOL architectures) upon evaluation with Kaggle competition authors (Prof. Emma Lundberg's Lab)
- Summarised project to Health Intelligence Lab leadership at End-of-Internship talk

Sep 2016 -Aug 2017

Industrial Trainee @ Crescendo Biologics Ltd.

- | Cambridge, UK · Engineered a novel, universal tool cell line for early drug discovery, i.e. phage
- display selection & functional screening of antibody fragment onco-therapeutics • Presented project outcomes to senior scientists & company management board

Jun 2016 -Sep 2016

Cancer Research UK Intern @ Cambridge University | Cambridge, UK

· S. Bohndiek Lab: Characterised anti-angiogenic drug effects via breast cancer cell-based growth, viability assays to evaluate oxygen role in cancer progression

Jun 2015 -Aug 2015

Visiting Scholar, Whitehead Institute @ MIT | Cambridge, USA

· R. Weinberg's Lab: Investigated determinants of cancer cell invasion, metastasis & tumour stroma immunomodulation upon epithelial-to-mesenchymal transition

Teaching Experience

Mar 2020 -Present

Graduate Teaching Assistant @ UCL BIOC0016 module | London, UK

• Co-designed an iPython-based practical session for 70+ undergraduate students for introductory concepts in bioimage analysis, bioinformatics & machine learning to hand-label image mini-dataset & train simplified classifier of cell mitotic state

Jan 2021 -Dec 2021

Google Certified Trainer for AI Tech & Tools | Bratislava, Slovakia

• Empowering non-tech professionals by leveraging their expertise & leadership in Al tech field via Al-basics talks & workshops with Google Slovakia outreach team

May 2021

"Smart Microscopy" Workshop @ ZEISS | Gothenburg, Sweden

• Trained 30+ intermediate-level attendees at "Train Your Own Model" hands-on workshop session to use (bio)image analysis tools (napari, jupyter notebooks) to annotate cell imaging data to train deep learning model to classify cell cycle state

Jun 2020

"Introduction to Deep Learning" @ UCL Cancer Domain | London, UK

- Delivered beginner-friendly masterclass series for 100+ interdisciplinary scientists with real-life examples of deep learning-based bioimage analysis from PhD project
- Contrasted deep learning to other computer vision methods, demonstrated the utility & benefits, emphasised fundamentals of 'learning' component, outlined common evaluation metrics & listed current challenges in computer vision field

Awards & Scholarships

- 2021 30 under 30 @ Forbes Slovakia
- 2019 European Union Council Delegate
- 2019 Travel Grant: Students to the World
- 2019 **Travel Grant**: Talents of New Europe
- 2017 United Nations Assembly Delegate
- 2017 GSK Healthcare STEM Awardee
- 2014 'Absolute Winner at the Festival of Science & Technology' @ AMAVET
- 2013 'The Special Award by the Dean of the Faculty of Natural Sciences'

Science Popularisation —— & Lay Audience Engagement

- 2022 Reflect Festival | Limassol, Cyprus
- 2015 Universal Expo Milano | Milan, Italy
- 2014 Intel ISEF Finals | Los Angeles, USA
- 2013 Global Scholars Programme @ ALA | Johannesburg, South Africa
- · 2013 International Congress of Young Investigators | Zaragoza, Spain

Language Skills

Slovak native proficiency

Czech bilingual proficiency

Enalish full professional proficiency

IELTS & iBT TOEFL language test certificates

limited working proficiency German

High-school certificate; German evening classes

Hobbies & Interests ———

- · Ballroom dancing; standard & Latin style (UK national partner competitions level)
- Bachata & salsa social dancing (int/adv)
- Long-distance running (half-marathons)
- Playing tennis (competitively at school)

General -

- Member of the University of London DanceSport Society (active competitor)
- · Member of London Stem Cell Network
- Member of British Pharmacol Society
- EU / Slovak driving licence | B type
- First aid training course certificate

Academic Referees

- Prof Guillaume Charras (UCL)
 - PhD thesis project primary advisor
- Dr Alan R. Lowe (UCL; Alan Turing Inst.)
 - PhD thesis project secondary advisor
- Prof Geraint Thomas (UCL)
 - LIDo PhD Programme Deputy Director

Leadership & Teamwork Experience

Sep 2019 -Student Ambassador, LIDo PhD Programme @ UCL Present • Outlined programme structure & shared own experience with new student cohorts · Guided individual students through responsibilities with changing rotation projects 2015 -Jury Member, LEAF Award @ LEAF | Bratislava, Slovakia 2017 • Shortlisted self-driven, talented students with community involvement in jury team University Mentor, Talent Guide @ LEAF | Bratislava, Slovakia 2016 -

· Counselled college choices with gifted high-schoolers & edited personal statements

Specialist Trainings & Summer Schools

-			
Sep 2022	Weizmann Institute of Science • 'International School of Biological Physics of Cells', part of EN	Rehovot, Israel MBO PhysCell 2022	
Apr 2022	Institut Curie & Sorbonne Université 'International course of Cell Biology & Cancer' with the 'Science Course of Cell Biology & Cancer' with the 'Science Course C	Paris, France ce & Life' workshop	
Dec 2020	Jumping Rivers Ltd. • Two intermediate courses: 'Machine Learning with Python', 'F	London, UK Python & Tensorflow	
Aug 2019	University of Hong Kong Practical course 'Advanced Imaging: Deep Learning in Live Im	Hong Kong laging & Cell Biology	
Jun 2019	University of Genova • 'Machine Learning Crash Course' covering theoretical foundations	Genova, Italy ions & core concepts	
Sep 2016	University of Cambridge • Two beginners courses: 'Solving Biological Problems', 'Statisti	Cambridge, UK cal Analysis' using R	
Jun - Jul 2012	Johns Hopkins University Interactive class 'The History of Disease' by Centre for Talenton	Baltimore, USA ed Youth (CTY JHU)	

2018

Invited Talks			
2021	Speaker Machine Learning Methods Advances @ Recursion CytoData Society Meeting Speaker Al Microscopy Symposium @ The Allen Institute for Brain Science & AlVIA Panelist "See the Hidden": Future of Al in Microscopy Workshop @ Leica Microsystems Panelist "Women in Al for Global Health" Session @ Mozilla Festival Tech Conference		
2020	Speaker UCL BioImage Analysis Interest Group @ Laboratory of Molecular Cell Biology Speaker Imperial College Brain Sciences Seminar @ UK Dementia Research Institute Speaker Python Software Foundation Pro Network Meetup @ #PyLadies Dublin		

| EMBO Workshop: Physics of Cells (PhysCell Conf 2022) @ Ein Gedi, Israel

Contributed Talks

2022 Poster

	Speaker	The Crick Annual PhD Student Symposium @ The Francis Crick Institute
2021	Poster Poster Poster Speaker	Women in Machine Learning (WiML) Workshop @ NeurIPS Conference Crick Biolmage Analysis Symposium (CBIAS) @ The Francis Crick Institute Women in Data Science (WiDS) Worldwide Conference @ Stanford University Virtual Seminars in Biomedical Science @ Imperial College London
2020	Poster Poster Speaker .	London Stem Cell Network Annual Symposium @ The Francis Crick Institute Society of Biomolecular Imaging & Informatics High Content Conference UCL Institute of Structural & Molecular Biology Postgraduate Symposium
2019	Speaker Speaker Poster .	UCL Institute of Structural & Molecular Biology Friday Wrap @ Birkbeck Quantitative Systems Biology Workshop @ King's College London UCL Graduate Student Symposium @ Francis Crick Institute

Publications

Ulicna, K., Vallardi, G., Charras, G. & Lowe, A.R. (2021). Automated deep lineage tree analysis using a Bayesian single cell tracking approach. Frontiers in Computer Science, Computer Vision: Methods & Tools for Bioimage Analysis | Frontiers | BioRxiv | GitHub repository

Ulicna, K., Ho, L.T.L., Soelistyo, C.J., Day, N.J. & Lowe, A.R. (2022). Convolutional neural networks for classifying chromatin morphology in live cell imaging. Methods in Molecular Biology, Chromatin Architecture, Springer Nature Protocols | Springer | GitHub repository